A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980 FA739G
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Address to the World Traffic Engineering Conference, Washington, D. C., August 21 (Reports 019258) (EA 61-4), 1961; Ylvisaker, Paul N. (Box 936, Sheet EA 61-4)
  "In recent months, a city has been forced by international events to become the decisive pawn in the present chessgame of man's destiny, and to shoulder the eternal problem of war or peace." [p. 1]
  India Reports Economics & Administration
- Bay area conference: "regional planning," Oakland, CA, March 2 (Reports 019259), 1963; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "That could be an exciting -- for whatever you may feel about New York (and Californians, being now the most populous state in the Union, can afford to be generous) -- the fact is New York is the liveliest and most powerful city of our age." [p. 1]
- Social and cultural goals for the metropolis, May 6 (Reports 019260), 1963; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  I am not sure that anyone can set goals for as large and diverse a community as a metropolis without resorting so some pretty broad and seemingly pious generalities. [p. 1]
  City and town life; Metropolitan areas; Cities and towns -- Growth; City planning; Cultural pluralism
- The approach of the Ford Foundation to the problems of American cities, October 1 (Reports 019261), 1963; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "This action brings to six the number of companion experiments in which the Ford Foundation has made, or is contemplating, major investments." [p. 1]
  Cities and towns -- Growth -- United States; City planning; Endowments
- New ideas for cities as learned from foundation grants, August 12 (Reports 019262), 1963; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "The accomplishments of foundations have been considerable;their potential is ever greater. But I am frank to say, I do not think the potential of philanthropy in contributing to the solution of community -- and especially urban community -- problems has
  Cities and towns -- Growth -- United States; City planning; Urban policy; Endowments
- Social bargaining and community welfare (Reports 019263), 1963; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  One of the themes we are all concerned with is the community. All of us are concerned with social change and with problem solving in order to advance the aspirations of our community. [p. 1]
  Social change; Cultural pluralism; Cities and towns -- Growth -- United States; City planning; Urban policy; Community development
- Regarding your community, November 11 (Reports 019264), 1963; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  It's in the law and on your conscience that you're to have due regard for the needs of the community you serve. [p. 1]
  Social change; Cultural pluralism; Community development; Cities and towns -- Growth
- New ideas for cities as learned from foundation grants (Reports 019265), 1964; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  I am often asked whether all the millions foundations have spent under the label of improving urban community life have yielded important results. [p. 1]
- Remarks at IISS meeting, Berlin (Reports 019266), 1985; Thomas, Franklin A.
  "Today is an extraordinarily happy occasion. In part, it is a coming of age celebration;in part a slightly belated silver anniversary of a great union between IISS and the Ford Foundation." [p. 1]
  Endowments -- Ford Foundation; International relations
- Remarks to the Society of Foreign Consuls, Berlin, May 22 (Reports 019267), 1985; Thomas, Franklin A.
  Visitors to the United States have often expressed surprise at the strength and extent of America's voluntary sector. [p. 1]
  Endowments -- Ford Foundation -- United States; Nonprofit organizations -- United States
- Speech for the permanent representatives to the United Nations, June 1 (Reports 019268), 1989; Thomas, Franklin A.
  "Visitors to the United States often express surprise at the strength and extent of America's Non-Profit Sector -- sometimes called the Independent Sector, the Voluntary Sector, or the Third Sector." [p. 1]
- Speech at Peter Stanley's inauguration as President of Pomona (Reports 019269), 1991; Thomas, Franklin A.
  "It is an honor and a pleasure for me to be with you today, as Peter and his family join their lives to the life of Pomona College." [p. 1]
  College presidents -- Inauguration -- United States; Universities and colleges -- United States
- De Witt lecture, November 19 (Reports 019270), 1965; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "The break from the church of my childhood, when it came, was agonizing and traumatic." [p. 2]
- A relevant Christ -- but a relevant church?, February 5 (Reports 019271), 1964; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "For the ideas which underlie our institutions have more meaning than ever, but the institutions themselves have been losing touch with current problems and circumstance." [p. 2]
  Social change; Social gospel; Jesus Christ -- Political and social views
- Paul Ylvisaker -- interview with US News and World Review (Reports 019272), 1964; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "We've become an urban, impersonal and sophisticated society. We've also grown weary of taxes and skeptical of large-scale efforts to solve problems." [p. 1]
  Social change -- United States; Discrimination -- United States; Poverty -- United States
- Not by brick and mortar alone, June 9 (Reports 019273), 1964; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "Address to the annual meeting of Louisville Central Area, Inc." [p. 1]
  Social change -- United States; Community development
- Conscience and the community (Reports 019274), 1964; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "Therefore, I would argue first--and last-- that broadcasters stretch their minds and resources to explore the uncertain and the unspecified in the open-ended charge they have been given." [p. 1]
  Social change -- United States; Community development -- United States; Cultural pluralism -- United States; Broadcasters -- United States
- Speech delivered at Conference on the Church and the City, October 13 (Reports 019275), 1964; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  My topic -- The Church in Public Affairs - builds on Biblical text: 'Render unto Caesar the things that are Caesar's.' [p. 1]
  Social change -- United States; Church and social problems
- The scholar and social needs, April 15 (Reports 019276), 1983; Thomas, Franklin A.
  "The issue-oriented sphere is occupied predominantly, but not exclusively, by the social sciences;the other is occupied predominantly, but not exclusively, by the humanities." [p. 2]
  Scholars -- United States; Social sciences -- United States
- Manpower and research needs of municipal government, May 31 (Reports 019277), 1963; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  The skills required to govern a modern urban community are of the highest order -- higher than those required by any of the single enterprises within it [p. 2]
  Municipal government -- United States; Research and development projects; Occupational training
- Resume of remarks at Institute of Modern Management, January 31 (Reports 019278), 1961; Ylvisaker, Paul N.
  "May I come directly to the central point of this address: we are living in an age of accelerating change, a time when the boundaries of our culture, our economy and our politics are being rapidly washed away and a larger, stranger and more complicated wo
  Social change; Political science
- Challenges and opportunities for the non-profit sector, September 16 (Reports 019279), 1988; Gaberman, Barry D.
  "To be sure, foundations are a very specialized and perhaps peculiar sub-sector of the non-profit world." [p. 2]
  Nonprofit organizations
- Informal remarks for the Ohio Association of Two-year Colleges (Reports 019280), undated; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Many institutions have long since abandoned the assumption or illusion that most students attend for two years, or that some or even a majority complete a two-year degree program in two years." [p. 1]
  Community colleges -- United States
- Realities and prospects, October 20 (Reports 019281), 1981; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "In order to think about the topic for this panel, 'Realities and Prospects,' we first need to be clear about the specific role of philanthrophy." [p. 1]
  Government aid -- Research -- United States; Endowments
- How a national foundation reponds to social change, November 18 (Reports 019282), 1981; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Looking at this history, I would like to argue that the phase I approach of fitting women's programs into existing categories had some clear benefits." [p. 3]
  Endowments -- United States; Social change; Women
- Realities of foundation giving, February 25 (Reports 019283), 1982; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "In 1970, it was estimated that there were 24,000 foundations in the U.S. Only 1.5% have any staff at all." [p. 1]
- Remarks on the role of foundations in relationships and developments in international affairs, August 3 (Reports 019284), 1982; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "What ought foundations do differently as a result of the dramatically changed federal, state and local relationsips and developments in international affairs?" [p. 1]
  Endowments -- United States; International cooperation
- Speech in Baltimore for city high schools, October 21 (Reports 019285), 1983; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Today, we are honoring the schools, we are celebrating their achievement." [p. 1]
  Endowments; Academic achievement; Public schools -- Baltimore (Md.)
- Commencement speech at South Mountain Community College, June 28 (Reports 019286), 1984; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Baccalaureate addresses -- South Mountain Community College; Community colleges
- Draft of remarks at the New school, December 15 (Reports 019287), 1983; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Education -- United States; Poor -- United States; Endowments
- Revson fellows, October 30 (Reports 019288), 1984; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Endowments; Scholarships
- Urban college transfer opportunities program, November 9 (Reports 019289), 1984; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Urban universities and colleges -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States
- Speech at Council on Foundations meeting for Community Foundations in Scottsdale, Arizona, October 16 (Reports 019290), 1986; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Community foundations; Endowments -- United States
- Remarks delivered at the Donors Forum 13th Annual Luncheon honoring Eleanor Petersen, March 18 (Reports 019291), 1987; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Poverty -- United States
- Remarks delivered at Concluding Luncheon of LISC Conference, April 3 (Reports 019292), 1987; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Poverty -- United States; Community foundations -- United States; Community development corporations -- United States
- Remarks delivered at the Portland City Club Luncheon, July 24 (Reports 019293), 1987; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Poverty -- Portland (Or.); Endowments -- Ford Foundation
- Comments at the National Network of Women's Funds, April 22 (Reports 019294), 1988; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Women; Endowments -- United States
- Remarks delivered at the Rochester Area Foundation, March 22 (Reports 019295), 1989; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Community foundations -- United States; Endowments
- Remarks delivered at the Salzburg Seminar, May 2 (Reports 019296), 1989; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Nonprofit organizations; Endowments
- Remarks delivered at the Community of Greater Lorain County Associates Dinner, November 30 (Reports 019297), 1989; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
- Draft of remarks delivered at the American Gas Association 1990 Consumer and Community Affairs Exchange, New York City, September 11 (Reports 019298), Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
- Remarks about foundations on the subject of media and public scrutiny, February 2 (Reports 019299), 1991; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
- Comments at the Symposium for the Global Partnership Fund (Reports 019300), 1991; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Private foundations have several roles in the U.S. In many instances they are a source of what we would call 'charity.' [p. 1]
- Remarks at the Metropolitan Atlanta Community Foundation, October 23 (Reports 019301), 1991; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Beyond this, the Metropolitan Atlanta Community Foundation is part of the growing numbers of community foundations around the U.S. which are serving as models for new foundations overseas." [p. 1]
  Endowments -- United States; Community foundations -- United States
- Remarks at the Council on Foreign relations "New Voices" Dinner, March 10 (Reports 019302), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
- Strengthening local philanthropy, April 20 (Reports 019303), 1993; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Remarks made at the Bellabio Study and Conference Center. [p. 1]
- The role of NGOs and women in meeting the challenges of a new era, June 17 (Reports 019304), 1993; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Speech given at IIE to a group of Japanese and American women working in NGOs. [p. 1]
  Non-governmental organizations; Women
- Comments at the Tenth Anniversary Celebration for the Puerto Rico Community Foundation, May 19 (Reports 019305), 1995; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  We are here to celebrate a spectacluar achievement -- the completion of a decade of extraordinary work by the Puerto Rico Community Foundation. [p. 1]
  Community foundation
- Diversity and challenges for education, April 27 (Reports 019306), 1995; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  A portion of Ford's work falls under the headlline of multicultural education young people and adults. [p. 2]
  Education -- United States; Multicultural education -- United States
- Changing times/changing leadership: challenges to philanthropy, October 24 (Reports 019307), 1995; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Let me briefly outline some aspects of the transformed global environment to which our organizations must adapt. Some of the changes have been positive, such as the demise of oppressive systems like apartheid and communism, and the end of the Cold War."
- Remarks to the Conference Board, January 9 (Reports 019308), 1996; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Your conference program is built around the concept of 'reappraisal.' These days, all institutions -- government, private, and nonprofit -- are knee-deep in often wrenching reappraisal efforts." [p. 1]
  Endowments; Corporations; Community development
- The National Foundation for India: keynote address at the Fifth Anniversary Celebration, February 7 (Reports 019309), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943- (Box 890)
  We must remember that NFI had enormous challenges at the start. There was no institution like this in India. [p. 1]
  Endowments -- India
- Speech given at the National Conference of La Raza Annual Meeting, Denver, CO, July 17 (Reports 019310), 1996; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  The Ford Foundation and the National Council of La Raza have been partners since 1968. And our partnership has been significant. [p. 1]
- Comments to the Seattle Rotary Club, October 30 (Reports 019311), 1996; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Simply put, the Ford Foundation wants to find ways for businesses to contribute to the development of poor communities through core business activities." [p. 2]
- Comments to the Consultation on Comparative Human Relation Initiative - beyond racism: Brazil, South Africa and the United States in the twenty first century, April 2 (Reports 019312), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Wherever I went, most people, whether in rich or poor, old or new countries, expressed concern about the speed, depth and scale of change which was creating profound and sometimes negative effects." [p. 2]
  Endowments -- United States; Human rights; Multiculturalism
- Detroit Women's Economic Club, April 17 (Reports 019313), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Families are the nucleus of society, so we dare not take them for granted. Rather, we must grasp their importance and strengthen them." [p. 2]
  Family -- United States; Poor -- United States; Endowments -- United States
- Comments at the Women and Philanthropy LEAD! Award, May 4 (Reports 019314), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Women's rights; Endowments -- United States; Award presentations
- Comments at the Ms. Foundation Dinner, May 29 (Reports 019315), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
- Remarks at the Donors' Forum of Chicago, June 12 (Reports 019316), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  ...Men and women repeatedly told me that the extraordinary degree of change had left them with deep seated feelings of uncertainty and a loss of confidence in their ability to influence the powerful forces around them. [p. 1]
- Remarks at the National Committee on United States-China Relations Dinner, September 8 (Reports 019317), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  The Foundation has been supporting work related to China since 1952. We have been motivated by the belief that knowledge of different cultures is the first step toward mutual understanding. [p. 1]
  Endowments; International relations
- Comments at the CEO Summit on Relinking Life and Work, September 15 (Reports 019318), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  The traditional view is that these matters are in conflict -- productivity gains too often come at the expense of accommodations of workers' family and community responsibilities. [p. 2]
  Work and family -- United States; Endowments
- The meaning of globalization, September 29 (Reports 019319), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "What is globalization? Globalization is the rapid and accelerating worldwide movement of communications, goods, capital, people and ideas." [p. 1]
  Globalization
- Statement before the Subcommittee on Government Management, Information, and Technology of the Committee on Government Reform and Oversight, October 31 (Reports 019320), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "In the mid-1980's, one began to hear increasing expressions of doubt in the United States about the ability of government, as well as those who served in government, to perform." [p. 1]
  Government productivity -- United States
- Remarks at the Greater Kansas City Community Foundation's Annual Donor Luncheon, November 24 (Reports 019321), 1997; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Today, society's tectonic plates seem to be on the move. On one level, the world of the 1990s is rich in positives. The end of the Cold War and apartheid and the welcome spread of democracy have feed new energies." [p. 2]
  Endowments; Generosity
- Remarks at gathering of San Diego Foundation's Corporate CEO partners, Major Donors, Community Organizations, February 3 (Reports 019322), 1998; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "This is a particularly interesting time in which to be in such a foundation, as this seems to be a time of unusual openness to new ideas." [p. 1]
  Endowments; Corporations
- Remarks at the Conference Board's meeting, Miami, FL, February 9 (Reports 019323), 1998; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "With greater influence comes greater responsibility. There is heightened public expectation that corporations, with record profits, global power, and rich reserves of talent, will also be a positive force in society." [p. 1]
- Remarks at the Tucson Community Foundation's Annual Community Meeting, Tuscon, AZ, April 16 (Reports 019324), 1998; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "...For old divisions among government, the private sector, and philanthropic institutions are become obsolete." [p. 1]
- Remarks at the Metro NYC ACE/NNWL, April 30 (Reports 019325), 1998; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "At Ford, the process began with talks I had with each trustee. I then spent several months in staff discussions about the role of the foundation and how we could best advance our goals in this fast-changing environment." [p. 1]
- Remarks at the Philadelphia Award Van Pelt Auditorium, Philadelphia, PA, June 23 (Reports 019326), 1998; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  We are honoring two extraordinary women tonight. [p. 1]
  Award presentations; Arts; Endowments -- United States
- Remarks at the Fannie Mae Press Release, New York, NY, July 23 (Reports 019327), 1998; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Financial assets are crucial to the economic well-being of families. They provide a cushion against unexpected expenses or crises, thereby helping to increase family stability." [p. 1]
  Community development; Community development corporations -- Endowments
- Remarks at the American Academy of Arts and Sciences Induction Ceremony, Cambridge, MA, Octover 3 (Reports 019328), 1998; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Many of us in the U.S. owe much of what we have accompished and will accomplish to non-profit organizations - among them many of our great universities and colleges, our settlement houses, our human rights organizations, our religious institutions and ot
  Nonprofit organizations -- Endowments
- Moral resources and social change, November 5 (Reports 019329), 1998; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Keynote address at the Miami Donors Forum's 10th Anniversary meeting, Miami, FL." [p. 1]
  Endowments; Social change
- Remarks at the Charlotte-Mecklenburg Education Foundation, Charlotte, NC, February 9 (Reports 019330), 1999; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  We are inspired by organizations that bring together members of the community in efforts to improve the public schools. [p. 1]
  Education -- Endowments -- United States
- Remarks at the Scrivner Award Presentation Council on Foundation Annual Conference, New Orleans, LA, April 20 (Reports 019331), 1999; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "This a great success story. In fact, the innovative Community Foundation of Puerto Rico has become one of the great models for community foundations throughout the world, particularly in poor countries." [p. 2]
  Community foundations -- Endowments; Award presentations
- Remarks at the LEAD Award Presentation Council on Foundation Annual Conference, New Orleans, LA, April 18 (Reports 019332), 1999; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  Award presentations -- Marie Wilson
- Remarks at the New York Regional Grantmakers Association Annual Meeting, May 11 (Reports 019333), 1999; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  The end of the 20th century and the approach of the new millennium provide the proper moment to reflect on the privilege we have working in philanthropy. [p. 1]
- Tribute to Adele Simmons, President, MacArthur Foundation, June 16 (Reports 019334), 1999; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  I am honored to be among those paying tribute to Adele Simmons and the MacArthur Foundation tonight. [p. 1]
  Endowments; Decorations of honor
- Remarks at the 1999 Conference of Ford Fellows (Reports 019335), Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "As you may know, thus far the current program's 18 year history, over 1800 scholars have received support and gone on to important academic posts." [p. 1]
- Remarks at the National Center For Non-Profit Boards Luncheon, Washington, D.C., November 15 (Reports 019336), 1999; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-
  "Board diversity has a long tradition at Ford, but we must constantly work at it, since our system of board rotation means that Trustees periodically retire and need to be replaced by new people." [p. 2]
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations